A Finding Aid to the Richard Haas Papers, 1937-2012, bulk 1970-2012, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Richard Haas papers
1937-2012
Archives of American Art
Haas, Richard, 1936-
AAA.haasrich
Archival Resource Key
6 Linear feet
The Richard Haas papers measure 6 linear feet and are dated 1937 to 2012, bulk 1970-2012. His work and career as a muralist, printmaker, and educator are documented by correspondence, writings, printed material, sketchbooks, and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Richard Haas in 2012.
Related Material
An interview of Richard Haas conducted January 13 and March 16, 2009, by Avis Berman, for the Archives of American Art's U.S. General Services Administration, Design Excellence and the Arts oral history project, at Haas' studio, in New York, N.Y.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Richard Haas (b. 1936) is a mural painter of "architecture of illusion," his term describing the trompe l'oeil architectural subjects for which he is best known. His work as a printmaker also focuses on architecture, with iconic buildings of New York and other cities serving as subject matter. Hass is also an educator who has taught painting and printmaking at University of Minnesota, Michigan State University, Bennington College in Vermont, and School of Visual Arts in New York City.
During World War II, the Haas family moved from Spring Green, Wisconsin to Milwaukee. As a teenager, Richard spent two summers working with his great uncle, a master stone mason employed by Frank Lloyd Wright at Taliesin. He proved to be less interested in stonework than in exploring Wright's library and watching the young architects draw. He considered becoming an architect, but eventually concluded the artistic side of architecture was more attractive than the day to day work of an architect.
After graduating from the University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee (B.S., 1959), Hass worked as an art teacher in a Milwaukee high school. He attended graduate classes at University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee where visiting artist Jack Tworkov was his teacher. At the University of Minnesota (M.F.A., 1964), Haas studied with Peter Busa and Malcolm Myers. As an assistant professor at Michigan State University from 1964 to 1968, Haas's colleagues included Angelo Ippolito and Charles Pollock, and he met a number of important artists and critics who visited the campus. Haas moved to New York City in 1968 and soon accepted a part-time position teaching printmaking at Bennington College. He commuted weekly between New York and Vermont for the next decade.
During the 1960s Haas was a Color-field painter. He also continued making etchings and lithographs, and by 1970 several galleries were selling his architectural prints. His first outdoor mural, painted in the So Ho section of New York City in 1975, attracted attention and commissions followed. Mural commissions include: Boston Architectural Center (1977); Edison Bothers Store, Inc., St. Louis (1984); Home Savings of America, multiple locations in Florida and California (1990-1991); City of Huntsville, Texas (1991); Federal Building and Courthouse, Kansas City, Kansas (1994); and Yorkville Mural, New York City (2004.)
Haas, who began exhibiting while still a student, has participated in a large number of group shows and enjoyed many solo exhibitions. He was elected a National Academician, National Academy of Design, was granted a Guggenheim Fellowship, and has been a MacDowell Fellow. Among other honors, Haas has received the American Institute of Architects Medal of Honor, New York City Municipal Art Society Award, Doris C. Freedman Award for Public Art, and the Jimmy Ernst Award of the American Academy of Arts and Letters.
Mr. Haas, who works in New York City, is represented by David Findlay, Jr. Gallery. His wife, Katherine Sokolnikoff, is a sculptor and arts administrator; they live in Yonkers, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The Richard Haas papers measure 6 linear feet and are dated 1937 to 2012, bulk 1970-2012. His work and career as a muralist, printmaker, and educator are documented by correspondence, writings, printed material, sketchbooks, and photographs.
Haas's correspondence relates to commissions, exhibitions, lectures, publications, teaching, and other professional activities. Correspondents include clients, galleries, professional organizations, critics, artists, architects and others. Also found is small amount of personal correspondence. Writings and notes by Haas include artist's statements, notes, lectures, a travel diary, papers and class notes from his undergraduate and graduate student days. Writings about him are a New Museum exhibition catalog text and a student paper. Subject files relate to Haas's professional activities and interests. They document exhibitions and projects, relationships with galleries, membership and participation in various organizations, and routine business matters. Sketchbooks (17 volumes) contain drawings, sketches, and a few watercolors, along with scattered writings and notes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1990, 2009 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1964-2008 (Box 1; 1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1954-2012 (Box 2; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1970-2011 (Boxes 2-4; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1956-2012 (Boxes 5-6; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, 1954-2005 (Box 6; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, 1976-2009 (Box 6; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1937-2006 (Box 6; 0.1 linear feet)
Educators -- New York (State) -- New York; Watercolors; Sketchbooks; Travel diaries; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Drawings; Sketches; Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Art -- Study and teaching; Photographs
- Biographical Materials, 1990; 2009; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Included with program for his father's memorial service are a few loose sheets with notes for Hass's remarks and the sketches he made for the program. Also found is a copy of the invitation to a dinner celebrating his wife's birthday.
  - Family, 1990; 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1964-2008; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1
  Most of Haas's correspondence concerns professional matters such as commissions, lectures, publication permissions, teaching, and publicity. Correspondents include clients and potential clients, galleries, professional organizations, critics, artists, and architects. Also found is a small amount of personal correspondence that includes a few letters from his father and brother, invitations, and routine social correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged in rough alphabetical order. Additional correspondence is scattered throughout the subject files (Series 4).
  - A, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1977-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D, 1980-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E, 1981-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - F, 1964-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - G, 1978-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - H, 1977-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - I-K, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - L, 1987-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - N, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - O, 1977-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - P, 1979-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - R, 1977-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - S, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - T, 1980-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - U-V, 1972-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - W, 1978-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Y-Z, 1975-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Unidentified, 1967-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1954-2012; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2
  Scope and Contents
  Richard Haas's writings include artist's statments, lecture notes, and travel diary, along with his student notes and papers. Notebooks include Uiversity of Minnesota class notes, writings on art topics and other stubjects, as well as general notes and lists. The majority of the college papers were written when Haas was a graduate student at University of Minnesota; though one or two may date from his undergraduate years at the University of Wisconsin. The travel diary contains brief daily entries about a trip to China and Japan, October 8-Novemer 1, 2007. Entries dated December 25, 1911-January 13, 2012 record a trip to London, Abu Dhabi, Athens, Barcelona, and Rome. The volume's final few pages contain undated architectural drawings and Hyatt Home project notes, 2009.
  Writings about Haas are the text of an exhibition catalog and a student paper.
  Arrangement
  Additional writings are found among the subject files (Series 4) and in several sketchbooks (Series 7).
  - By Haas, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - College Papers, circa 1954-circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - Lectures and Talks, 1983-1984; 1989-circa 2003; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Notebooks, circa 1961-circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-21)
    - Notes, Bennington College, circa 1975-circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notes, California Trip, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, circa 1970s; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Statements, 1979; 1983; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Travel Diary, 2007; 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - About Haas - Manuscript of Exhibition Catalog, circa 1978-circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - About Haas - Student Paper, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Subject Files, 1970-2011; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  Subject files relate to Haas's professional activities and interests. They document his membership and participation in various organizations, relationships with galleries, and the writing and production of the catalogue raisonné of his prints.
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  - AIA [The American Institute of Architects] Correspondence, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Art Commission of the City of New York, 1978-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Break-Down Project Expenses, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Brooke Alexander Inc., 1978-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32-37)
  - "Buildings Reborn,", 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Catalogue Raisonné The Prints of Richard Haas: A Catalogue Raisonné: 1970-2004, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - Catalogue Raisonné, 2000-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Gifts, 2003-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Given/Sold, 1999-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Print Sale Records/Contract, 2003-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Promotion, 2005-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Research, Publishers, 1994-circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Century Association, 1997-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Century Association - Letters of Reference, 2003-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Century Association - Logan Delany, Jr., 2005-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Century Associaiton - Recommendations, 1985-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cooper-Hewitt Museum Lecture and Exhibit, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Delahunty, 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Exhibit at Rhona Hoffman Jan. 1990, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Exhibitions, 1978-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16-21)
  - Flood, 1986-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Jeff Green, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Haas-Sokolnikoff RTD [Rapid Transit District] Proposal, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Interview, Barbaralee Diamonstein, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Introduction to Great Walls of China by Frank Palaia, 1984, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Itineraries, circa 1992-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Japan Exhibition, "The Trick", 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - John Nichols Printmakers and Publishers, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - John Skoze Prints, 1985-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Chelsea Report, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Lecture Correspondence, 1982-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Mauss, Peter, 1983-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nashville Talk, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Academy of Design, 2010-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Phone and Travel Sheets, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Presentation, Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Presentation, Interior Design Conference, Aspen, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Presentation, International Muralists, Montreal, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Prints Lent Out, 1983-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Public Art Fund, Inc., 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Quincy Adams Garage, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Recommendations, 1997-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Rhona Hoffman Gallery/Young Hoffman Gallery, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rhona Hoffman Gallery, 1983-1984; 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - Rizzoli Book, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
  - SALAI [Stencil Artisans League, Inc.] Convention, Chicago, 2005-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - SCAD - Savannah College of Art and Design Lecture, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - School of Visual Arts, 1979-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Screens - Steve Gano, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Speaking Engagements, 1989-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Squat Theatre, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Storefront for Art and Architecture, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Texas Art Educators, 2000-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Texas Art Educators Magazine Cover Article, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Trip to Israel, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Trompe l'oeil Festival, Lodi, Italy, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - VAGA [Visual Artists and Galleries Association, Inc.], 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Walker Art Center, "Eight Artists - The Illusive Image,", 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Westchester Arts Council, 1990-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Young Hoffman Gallery (pre 1983), 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Printed Material, 1956-2012; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  Printed material mentions Haas or contains reproductions of his work. Among the miscellaneous printed items are newsletters, calendars, press releases and publicity surrounding his work.
  - Clippings, undated; 1964-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-14)
  - Exhibition Announcements, undated; 1963-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1976-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17-21)
  - Lecture Announcements, 1977-1998; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items, undated; 1975-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23-27)
  - Periodicals, 1956-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 28-30)
  - Periodicals, 1994-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Print Advertisements, 1985-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Print Catalogs, 1972-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Reproductions, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Artwork, 1954-2005; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 6
  Artwork consists of sketches and drawings. Those of Wyllie House and the dam at Taliesin were done when, as a teenager, Haas spent time at Taliesen with his stonemason great uncle who worked for Frank Lloyd Wright. Sketches and drawings done at meetings are identified portrait heads in pencil. Project studies are in pencil and ink. In addition to original drawings, some photocopies are interspersed.
  - Wyllie House and Dam at Taliesin, 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Hudson River Museum Board Meeting, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - National Academy Sketches, undated; 2001-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Skowhegan Board Retreat, 2005 January 17; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Project Studies, Unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Sketchbooks, 1976-2009; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 6
  Sketchbooks (17 volumes) contain pencil drawings and sketches including a few in colored pencil; also found are some drawings in ink and colored marker, along with a few watercolor paintings. Many volumes contain writings and notes, including: an artist's statement, notes for Clement Greenberg's lecture at Bennington College, trip itineraries, a list of photographs ordered from the Library of Congress, travel expense records, and project notes.
  Arrangement is chronological.
  - Volume 1, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Volume 2, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Volume 3, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Volume 4, circa 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Volume 5, circa 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Volume 6, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Volume 7, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Volume 8, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Volume 9, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Volume 10, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Volume 11, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Volume 12, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Volume 13, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Volume 14, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Volume 15, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Volume 16, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Volume 17, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Photographs, 1937-2006; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 6
  Photographs from Haas' childhood are snapshots of him with his siblings and parents. Studio portraits include a high school graduation picture and another taken while he was in the U.S. Army. Also found are views of Haas with his artwork and a group photograph of David Findlay Jr. Gallery artists. Photographs of probable relatives - most likely grandparents and parents - are unidentified. Among these family photographs are views of Haas's father and/or great uncle at their butcher shop in Spring Green, Wisconsin.
  - Richard Haas, with Family and Colleagues, 1937-2006; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Relatives (?), undated; circa 1940-circa 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 30)